Okay, בוקר טוב boker tov everybody.
We pick up today's דף daf is on... what's going on here?
Stop this thing again. Okay. All right. Fine. Hold on.
All right. בוקר טוב boker tov everybody. We start today with... hold
on. We start today on קטז. kuf tet zayin. Today's דף daf
is קטז kuf tet zayin 116. And we pick up at the
top of קטז kuf tet zayin actually. We are a little bit
ahead. So, let me also review a point from yesterday which maybe
wasn't clear. The question in the גמרא Gemara is that first of
all we were dealing with issues about witnesses testifying to certain specifics
around the death of a man and whether the woman could remarry,
the wife could remarry. On the one hand the concern that when
the woman is reporting it she might have been reporting stuff based
on impressions and not concrete
facts, אמר בדמי, amar bedami, or she drew certain conclusions which maybe
she's not even aware that she's drawing those conclusions and she's stating
them as facts. But then the גמרא Gemara goes on to discuss
times when look, we don't always have the facts and sometimes maybe
we and even if we know the concrete facts we won't have
all of them and maybe we are entitled to draw certain conclusions.
And that was questions about drawing a man, a drowned man out
of the water and a charred body, etc. So now the גמרא
Gemara deals with something which I think intersects those two issues, deals
with a case about a message that was sent that יצחק ריש
גלותא, Yitzchak Reish Galuta, the son of the sister of רב ביבי,
Rav Bibi, died. And the question is: is this the person that
we know of that name? So on the one hand it's relevant
because it's a question about testifying to somebody's death and us being
able to act on the information. But it's also relevant because it's
a question about knowing certain facts and drawing certain conclusions, right? We
have the facts of the person's name. Is that enough context in
order to allow us to sort of assume who that person is?
Now of course what is funny about that story is that we're
dealing with this ריש גלותא Reish Galuta who is, you know, the
head of the Exilarch there. It does not seem- how many ריש
גלותא Reish Galutas were there? So I really don't understand that. You
know, maybe they didn't say he was the ריש גלותא- Reish Galuta
I really can't understand that.
Could it be that that term was used broadly applied for
people who had some sort
of local
local rulers?
Okay, so I'd have to be something like that or else it
doesn't really make any sense. So maybe it is a more not
referring to the single ריש גלותא Reish Galuta but some type of
a type of a political official.
But still, the son of the sister
of רב ביבי- Rav Bibi Right, still there's a question how many
people fit that description. Anyway, so then the גמרא Gemara introduces a
debate of אביי Abaye and רבא Rava about whether we're concerned with
somebody else with that name and whether we would have to check
the entire region in order to make sure that there is nobody
else of that name. And it gives an example here about, you
know, let's pick up from this again from the bottom because it'll
reorient us and also a little I want to clarify a point
that I did not make yesterday. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אמר אביי מנא אמינא לה Amar Abaye, mina amina la?
So we're about ten lines from the bottom on קטו עמוד ב,
kuf tet vav amud bet, the line right above the little א
Aleph in parentheses. אמר אביי מנא אמינא לה Amar Abaye, mina amina
la? Where do I know to say that we're concerned that somebody
else might have the same name? דהוא גיטא דאשתכח בנהרדעא, dehu gita
de’ishtakach bin'harda’a, there was a גט get found in נהרדעא, Neharda’a, וכתיב
ביה vechativ beih בצד פלוניא מתא, tzad plonya masta, by the side
of פלוניא plonya the city, אנא אנדולינאי מנהרדעא, ana andulinay m'neharda’a, I
אנדולינאי Andulinay of נהרדעא, Neharda’a, פטרית פטריכת פלונית איתתי, patrit patrichat pelonit
iteti, I have divorced so-and-so my wife.
And that was it. So he had identified himself, אנדולינאי, Andulinay, he
was from the city of נהרדעא, Neharda’a, we knew the name of
his wife, so and we presumably knew somebody who matched that description.
And nevertheless, although we knew somebody who matched that description, ושדרה אבוה
דשמואל לקמיה דרבי יהודה נשיאה, veshadrach avuha de-Shmuel lekamei de-Rabbi Yehuda Nesiah,
the father of שמואל Shmuel sent it to רבי יהודה נשיאה, Rabbi
Yehuda Nesiah, the grandson of רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi, and
wanted to know do we have to worry that there might be
somebody else that fits that description or can we go based on
the person that we know that you know assume it's referring to?
ואמר ליה ve-amar leih and he said back to him, ושלח ליה,
veshadrach leih, תיבדוק נהרדעא כולה, tivdu neharda’a kula, you have to check
all of נהרדעא Neharda’a to determine that there is nobody else. You
cannot just assume oh I know that guy. You have to make
sure that there is no one else. So in general you are
concerned that there might be somebody else who fits that description.
Her name was not written? It was!
So it's not only his name and the his name place but
also the name of the wife. But maybe there's somebody else that
matches those details. ורבא אמר, ve-Rava amar, and רבא Rava says no,
that can't really be the requirement because אם איתא, im ita, if
we are concerned about that, יבדקו כל עלמא איבעי ליה, yivdu kol
alma iba'i leih, it's not enough to check נהרדעא Neharda’a you'd need
to check the whole world. Because maybe there's a guy that used
to live in נהרדעא Neharda’a and fits that description and now he
is living somewhere else. So therefore you have to go as- so
you know it's sort of like an אין לדבר סוף. ein davar
sof. אלא, ela, so there really was not that
requirement and משום כבודא דאבוה דשמואל הוא דשלח הכי. mishum k'voda de-avuha
de-Shmuel hu de-shadrach hachi. He told it because you know the father
of שמואל Shmuel asked a question he didn't want to say stupid
question, he said fine go ahead check it out, but really there
would be the- really no requirement. So that's רבא Rava's position, that
there really is no requirement, if it looks like somebody the name
fits, then wear it. אמר רבא מנא אמינא לה Amar Rava, mina
amina la?
Where do I know this? That I say that you don't have
to worry, דהנו תרי שטרי דנפקי במחוזא, de-hanu terei shtarei di-nafki be-Mechuza,
two writs of debt that came out in Mechuza, which is Rava's
city, and it was written in them, חבי בר ננאי וננאי בר
חבי, Chavi bar Nanai ve-Nanai bar Chavi, two names that clearly were
very popular, Chavi the son of Nanai, Nan the son of Fred,
and Fred the son of Jan. Okay,
so these were the names, pretty popular names.
And the question is now, I misexplained this yesterday, if that word
misexplained, that these are not the names of both the creditor and
the debtor. These are just the names of the creditor. So the
creditors had very common names, and they were the ones, people who
had these names, you know, had the get. Let's say it has
two writs of debt coming from one guy by the name of
John Smith and the other guy by the name of, what's another
common name?
John Doe. Doe isn't such a common name anyway. And these are
the people that are holding these writs and they have the writs
of, they are the creditors, their names match the name in the
document, but they're very common names. Now, the name of the debtor
presumably is not so common. So presumably there is no question who
the debtor was, because what we're going to speak about now is
whether the circumstances can clarify that this genuinely is the creditor, but
the question never is discussed how do we know who the debtor
was. So I misexplained that yesterday. It actually is assumed that the
debtor is very clear and very explicit, there's no question about it.
But given that these names are somewhat common, can we really assume
that the person holding it is genuinely the creditor? Now you realize
that this is not exactly like the earlier cases. The earlier cases
we were dealing with uncommon names where we did not know that
anybody else had the same name, but on the other hand there
was no supporting evidence, it was a random letter we got that
so-and-so died. It was a get that we found on the street.
Here we're dealing with common names where we know that other people
have the same name. Go open up a phone book, you'll find
other people with the same name, so we know there are other
names, but on the other hand there's supporting evidence because it's being
held by the person that has that name. So it's somewhat of
an analogy of these different cases and Rashi makes that point. So
if you look at Rashi, Rashi says, well let's read the Gemara
and then we'll read Rashi. ואגבי בהו רבה בר אבוה Ve-agbi behu
Rabba bar Avua זוזי zuzi and Rabba bar Avua, Rabba bar Avua
whatever used it to collect, he accepted these documents and he had
the people pay off the money, even though there could be a
claim that this wasn't the real creditor. והא הכי ve-ha hachi and
here חבי בר ננאי וננאי בר חבי במחוזא שכיחי טובא, Chavi bar
Nanai ve-Nanai bar Chavi be-Mechuza shechichi tuva,
there are a lot of people with those names, and nevertheless, he
said we don't have to worry about it. So here Rashi, here
Rashi makes the analogy, you're supposed to have a high degree of
identification, I suppose. So here Rashi says, שכיחי טובא, shechichi tuva, ואפילו
הכי מגבינן כשמוציאין שטר חוב על חבריו ולא חיישינן שמא אחר היה.
va-afillu hachi magbinan keshe-motzi'in shtar chov al chavreiv ve-lo chayshinan shema acher
haya. Okay, וכיון דלענין ממונא אף על גב דהוחזקו לא חיישינן.
ve-keivan de-le-inyan mamona af al
gav de-huchzeku lo chayshinan.
So here's the analogy. This is a case where it's only about
money and nevertheless we know that there definitely are people with other
names and nevertheless we're not worried about it, other people with the
same name, I'm sorry, with the same name and nevertheless we're not
worried about it. So לענין איסורא כי לא הוחזקו מי לא חיישינן.
le-inyan issura ki lo huchzeku mi lo chayshinan.
So I'm not going to say that you'll have the same standard
when it comes to allowing a woman to remarry, you'll have to
have a higher standard, but if when it comes to money we
don't care even though we know there are people with the same
name, then when it comes to allowing a woman to remarry we
shouldn't care as long as we don't concretely know that there's somebody
else who has the same name, okay? So it's a weird type
of an analogy because obviously you could make differences between them, but
the point just is we don't always worry about other people, you
know, about the possibility that it's referring to someone else. So here
we don't worry about it. Now we do have the supporting evidence
that the guy is holding it onto it, which is what Abaye's
retort, but here we don't worry about it even though we know
that there are other people with the same name. So certainly at
least when it comes to allowing a woman remarry we shouldn't be
concerned with it, at least in a case when we don't concretely
know that there's somebody else who has the same name.
Why can't the
debtor just identify the creditor, I don't know? Maybe he...
Maybe he's denying it, maybe it's a third party, maybe he's not
around. But yes, that's a good question. אביי, Abaye, אביי Abaye would
say that, למי נחוש לה? lemai nicheish leh? No, there's supporting evidence.
What do we need to be concerned about? אילו נפילה, ilu nefilah,
if it said that he dropped maybe this maybe the original creditor
dropped it and this guy picked it up, מיזהר זהירי בה, mizhar
zehiri bah, people are careful with their writs of debt. אילו פקדון,
ilu pikadon,
if we're concerned that maybe he gave it to this other guy
to watch for him and this guy is now stealing it essentially,
so no, כיון דשמיה כשמיה לא מפקדי גביה, keivan deshamei kishmei lo
mafkedi gabeih, nobody is stupid enough that if they have a IOU
written out to them that they would tap somebody else with the
exact same name as them watch it for them, okay? Because there's
got to be somebody else you could get to watch it for
you. So מה אמרת, mah amarta, so what do you want to
say? דילמא מזבניה, dilma mazzabneiah, maybe he gave it to this guy
and he actually intended to sell it to this guy but he
did not actually complete the sale and therefore that's the problem? So
this guy had got it not because it was dropped, got it
because he intended to buy it but maybe the sale hasn't completed.
No, אותיות נקנות במסירה, otiyot niknot bimesirah, once he gave it over
that does complete the sale so there's no case to be concerned
about. So אביי Abaye basically says there's nothing to be concerned about
in that case, obviously if the guy's holding on to it we
know we know that it's his. This by the way gets to
other types of questions in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia and elsewhere, you
know the whole problem of I'll just tell you a fascinating question
that תוספות Tosafot asks. תוספות Tosafot says I don't understand in all
דיני ממונות dinei mamonot we have the principle that חזקה מה שתחת
יד אדם הרי הוא שלו, chazakah mah shetachas yad adam harei hu
shelo, right? That what you're holding on to is assumed to be
yours. So why do we have to have this whole explanation of
no, he wouldn't have given it to someone else etc. or no
why does you know why don't we just say that that you
know that the fact that he's holding on to it allows us
to assume assume that it's his? Possession's nine tenths of the law
and that ends there. So תוספות Tosafot says yes, you know what's
assumed to be his because he's holding on to it? The piece
of paper, okay? You want to keep the piece of paper? Be
my guest. But to treat it as a document, to treat it
as a writ, to treat it as testimony that you have the
right debt, it's not enough to say you own the physical piece
of paper. There needs to be something that that basically you know
says that this is testifying about you. And that leads to the
interesting point about things like a גט get and a שטר חוב
shtar chov and so on, which is is that they actually are
testifying to the person that is bearing them, that is presenting it.
And that's sort of so part of the issue here and part
of an issue that comes up in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia as
well is the difference between like before when we talked about a
גט get that was found. If it's found on the street, how
much is it just a piece of paper and how much is
it doing an act of testifying? Part of what gives the שטר
shtar the power to be to speak, to act as a type
of a you know written testimony, to be seen as it's testifying
is that it's being presented by the right person, by the person
who it's written out to, you know? And therefore that's a basically
part of what אביי's Abaye response is. אביי's Abaye response is
if a גט get is found I'm going to be concerned about
who it's talking about. If a guy is presenting a document and
his name matches and it is doing an act of job of
testifying for him and therefore we're not going to be concerned.
So you don't have to worry about whether the שטר חוב shtar
chov is עדים edim and asking the עדים? edim?
What? Yeah, you don't have to talk to the עדים, edim, exactly.
Okay, in the case of the פקדון, pikadon, כיון דשמיה כשמיה לא
מפקדי גביה, keivan deshamei kishmei lo mafkedi gabeih, that maybe this guy
maybe this guy isn't the creditor but the guy the creditor asked
him to watch it for him? And then no, no creditor would
be stupid enough to ask a guy with the same name watch
his document for him. Okay, so this is the debate of אביי
Abaye and רבא, Rava, how much are we concerned by ממונות mamonot
when we know that there's somebody else with the same name, and
by איסור issur when we don't know that there's somebody else with
the same name, how much are we concerned that if we know
a guy that matches the description that we can assume that's the
guy? Or how much do we need like to go ahead and
to prove it
or alternatively to make sure our documents have a much higher degree
of specificity and of identification?
And in the case of the עדים edim with the not the
עדים edim but the גט, get, right? Where you have to search
the whole world or whatever it is, that gets to must be
a case where the עדים edim weren't around, otherwise you could just
ask them.
Well that's a good point, yes, if there's עדים edim you could
ask them. That's true. Now this in general is a principle like
I said that comes up in other גמרות, Gemarot, it's called הוחזקו
תרי יוסף בן שמעון. huchzeku terei Yosef ben Shimon. When we know
that there are two people with the name of יוסף בן שמעון
Yosef ben Shimon in the city, what do you do with documents
made out to יוסף בן שמעון? Yosef ben Shimon? Okay, so that's
when it's הוחזקו huchzeku and that's a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot question.
This is a question primarily about איסור, issur, about remarriage where it's
not הוחזקו, huchzeku, and nevertheless do we have to worry about it?
So let's take a look at the case. Okay, ההוא גיטא, hahu
gita, so now we're back to a גט, get, דאשתכח בסורא, de'ishtachach
beSura, that was found in סורא. Sura. We had נהרדעא, Nehardea, מחוזא
Mechuza and סורא, Sura, we're doing our whole you know touring of
cities in בבל, Bavel, right. So there was a גט get found
in סורא, Sura, וכתיב ביה הכי, veketiv beih hachi, and here's what
it was written: בסורא מתא, beSura mata,
in the city of סורא, Sura,
אנא, ana, I, ענן בר חייא נהרדעא, Anan bar Chiya Nehardea, Anan
bar Chiya from
Nehardea, פטרית ותרכית פלונית אינתתי, patrit vetarchit plonit inteti, I have divorced
so-and-so my wife, שרה Sarah my wife. So it was a guy
from נהרדעא Nehardea that was writing the גט get in סורא. Sura.
ובדקו רבנן מסורא ועד נהרדעא, uvedaku rabbanan miSura ve'ad Nehardea, and the
Rabbis checked from Sura until Nehardea. A סורא Sura to נהרדעא, Naharda,
so presumably they checked both cities. ולא הוי אנן בר חייא אחרינא
לבר מאנן בר חייא מחגרא דהוה בנהרדעא.
v'lo havei Anan bar Chiya acharina lebar mi'Anan bar Chiya
mi'Chigra de'hava be'Naharda. Okay and so they had one guy, what's not
a little clear about it is, they had one guy who they
assumed it was talking about, right? And that was the guy they
knew. Yeah, everybody knows חנן Chanan whatever, you know, חנן בר חייא
Chanan bar Chiya of נהרדעא. Naharda. They assumed they knew who it
was talking about, but they wanted to make sure they were following,
you know, אביי's Abaye approach, and they wanted to make sure there
was nobody else who might have matched that description. And from between
סורא Sura and נהרדעא Naharda they found one other guy who matched
that description, okay, אנן בר חייא לבר מאנן בר חייא מחגרא דהוה
בנהרדעא, Anan bar Chiya lebar mi'Anan bar Chiya mi'Chigra de'hava be'Naharda, and
he was from נהרדעא, Naharda, so that's אנן בר חייא Anan bar
Chiya from נהרדעא. Naharda. Wait, what's this מחגרא? mi'Chigra? What? I'm sorry,
מחגרא. mi'Chagra. I'm sorry, he was from חגרא, Chagra, but he had
been, you know, in נהרדעא, Naharda, okay? So he was,
חגרא Chagra was his original city of origin, but he had been
in נהרדעא, Naharda, and presumably his wife's name also matched the wife's
name of the גט, get, so they found somebody else other than
the guy they assumed it was who matched the description. Okay, the
only thing was, was that he was in נהרדעא, Naharda, and remember
the גט get at that time, and remember the גט get says
it was written in סורא, Sura, ואתו סהדי
ואמרי, v'atu sa'adi v'amri, and witnesses came and said, דההוא יומא דאיכתיב
האי
גיטא אנן בר חייא מחגרא גבן הוה, de'hahu yoma de'ichtiv hai gitta
Anan bar Chiya mi'Chigra gaban hava, that he was with us in
נהרדעא, Naharda, okay? So this guy whose name is אנן בר חייא
Anan bar Chiya from חגרא, Chigra, although presumably he was now taking
up residence in נהרדעא, Naharda, and there was testimony that he was
in נהרדעא Naharda at that date, okay? But it was in סורא.
Sura. No, the witnesses said he was in נהרדעא Naharda on that
day, okay, and the גט get was written in סורא. Sura. Okay,
so you get the case? גט get was written in סורא, Sura,
it identified a person, we assumed we knew who that person was,
we found another person who basically matched the description. He was residing
in נהרדעא, Naharda, so if he described himself as מנהרדעא mi'Naharda that
could have matched, okay, even though he originally was from this place
called חגרא. Chigra. Presumably his wife had the same name. So we
found another guy who matched the description other than the guy they
assumed it was, but we know that he wasn't in סורא Sura
on the date that the גט get says it was written in
סורא. Sura.
And they both divorced their wives at the same time?
No. Yeah, well, that's always the question. Why not ask the wives?
Whether one wife says she did receive it and the other wife
says she didn't receive it. I know, that's always the question about
what else are we finding out or not finding out about this
case. Let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara says, okay. אמר
אביי, Amar Abaye, so said אביי, Abaye, the point might be is
that, you know, and again this gets to the question about to
what degree does this document is it about circumstantial evidence or does
the document have to be testifying? Let's say this other guy says,
"No, I never divorced my wife," and the wife says, "No, he
never divorced me," and the guy we thought it was says, "I
divorced my wife," and she says, "Yes, he did divorce me." So
is that going to be enough? Or do we say since the
document itself doesn't testify to that fact, we can only sort of
assume that's back based on additional, you know, testimony and evidence, do
we really have like testimony that she's divorced, right? It raises interesting
questions. All along what we've been dealing with in יבמות Yevamos is
not formal testimony that the woman's husband has died, right? We've been
dealing with circumstantial evidence, better or worse circumstantial evidence. So it does
raise some interesting questions, now we're going to גט, get, not to
death, okay, but it does raise questions about how much is it
about evidence and how much is it about testimony. But Michael does
ask a very important question, which has to be addressed, like what's
everybody else saying? Anyway, let's take a look. We've got this guy
whose name matches, but he was in נהרדעא Naharda and the גט
get says he was in סורא. Sura. So do we have to
be concerned about it or not?
So, okay, אנן בר חייא מחגרא גבן הוה. Anan bar Chiya mi'Chigra
gaban hava. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, said אביי, Abaye, אף לדידי, af
l'didi, even according to me that in general I'm concerned with other
people with the same
name, דאמינא חיישינן d'amina chaishinan that I normally am concerned, הכא לא
חיישינן, hacha lo chaishinan,
here you actually checked. אביי Abaye says, "I only say you gotta
check. You did your job, you checked!" Ah, and and all we
found was one guy. We don't have to worry about this one
guy. Because we know what his story was. דקאמרי סהדי דבנהרדעא הוה.
de'kamri sa'adi de'vi'Naharda hava. The witnesses say he was in נהרדעא. Naharda.
מה בעי בסורא? ma ba'ei be'Sura? What would he be doing in
סורא Sura on the same time they said he was in נהרדעא?
Naharda? So אביי Abaye said, "I would have said, yes, you do
have to check, but then when you go ahead and check, then
if you know that you can eliminate people, then you can eliminate
them." So you found a guy with the same name, but you
were able to eliminate him. So it's not a problem, you did
your job, great, let's move on. That's what אביי Abaye says, would
say. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, now רבא Rava could say the opposite,
אף לדידי דלא חיישינן, af l'didi d'lo chaishinan, even I who normally
wouldn't have told you to bother to check, I'm not concerned with
people with the same names, הכא חיישינן, hacha chaishinan, now that you've
found a guy with the same name, I am concerned. What about
the fact that we could eliminate him? Because better not to have
checked, but now you've found a guy with the same name, you
can't ignore him. What about the fact that he was in נהרדעא
Naharda and the גט get was written in סורא? Sura? So דילמא
בגמלא פרחא
אזל, dilma begamla parcha azal, maybe he was in נהרדעא Naharda when
the witnesses said he was and then he got on a flying
camel, okay, a magic carpet, a speedy camel, and maybe he managed
to get to סורא Sura in time to write the גט. get.
Okay, אינמי... inami... קפיצה kfitzah
or he just did a big jump. תוספות Tosafot says that means
רש"י Rashi says it means with some type of magic in the
name of a שד sheid or a שד sheid or something. I
don't know. It sounds like he's saying absurd. It sounds like once
you have a concrete knowledge of another person, then you have a
concrete doubt and you cannot eliminate that doubt. Again, which is pretty
funny. But yes, at this point you would say it doesn't matter
even if it's logically impossible, the knowledge of a concrete other person
makes the problem. But the last one makes it a real reasonable
reason why to be concerned. אי נמי, I nami, wait, let's read
the third one which makes it the most reasonable reason, אי נמי,
I nami, מילי מסר, mili masar,
just because he was in נהרדעא Nehardea doesn't mean that a גט
Get wasn't being written for his name in סורא. Sura. Okay? He
doesn't, you don't have to be physically present when the גט Get
is being written. כי אמר להו רב ספרא לספרי, Ki amar lehu
Rav Safra lesafrei, like רב ספרא Rav Safra said to the scribes,
וכן אמר להו רב הונא לספרי, vechein amar lehu Rav Huna lesafrei,
and רב הונא Rav Huna said, כי יתביתו בשילי, ki yasbitu beShili,
if you're writing a גט Get in שילי, Shili, כתובו בשילי, kitvu
beShili, say that this גט Get was written, you know, in שילי,
Shili, even though the husband was actually אף על גב דמימסר מילי
בהיני, af al gav demimsar mili beHini, even though the husband told
you in היני, Hini, right, he told you in Boston write this
גט Get for my wife when and you happen to be in
New York, so the place name you put in, in, in the
גט Get is New York, is where it's being written, not where
the husband said. Even though, and here's the point, the language of
the גט Get is first person and the husband speaking, right, the
language of the גט Get is "I, John Smith, from so-and-so, divorce
my wife blah blah blah blah blah." So even though it's the
voice of the husband, you write the place not where the husband
commanded you and where the husband is, you write the place where
you are found, okay? So
and then the reverse, וכי יתביתו בהיני כתובו בהיני אף על גב
דמימסר מילי בשילי. veki yasbitu beHini kitvu beHini af al gav demimsar
mili beShili. Okay,
so anyway, so רבא Rava says just because it says that here
in סורא Sura we are writing this גט Get does not mean
the husband is in סורא, Sura, which is a very reasonable position.
If that's really true that that was the practice, one wonders why
אביי Abaye could feel otherwise, right, that the fact that it names
the place is completely irrelevant, the husband could have been somewhere else.
Okay, but what you do find out is that אביי Abaye and
רבא Rava when it comes to גט Get and when it comes
to messages that a guy has died, right, אביי Abaye is generally
concerned that he needs a higher standard to know we're talking about
the right person, and רבא Rava says that in general you don't
have to worry if somebody else might have the same name. If
you concretely find somebody with the same name, then רבא Rava might
say then you got a real problem, it's a lot harder to
eliminate somebody once you know, even if maybe the evidence does point
to eliminate it. And then the גמרא Gemara ends up: מאי הוי
עלה דשומשמי? Mai havah alah de-shumshumai? Goes back to the case which
we had thought was completely
bracketed. What happens to the whole case of the sunflower seeds? Do
we have to be concerned that they're different sunflower seeds or not?
רב יימר אמר לא חיישינן, Rav Yeimar amar lo chaishinan, we're not
concerned. רב אשי אמר חיישינן, Rav Ashi amar chaishinan, we are concerned.
והלכתא חיישינן, Ve-hilchata chaishinan, and we are concerned. Again, in a ממונות
mamonot case when there's sort of less maybe identifying marks. So all
of this is applying to like three or four different cases, each
one that could have its different level of standard. Right? The sunflower
seeds, same barrel, but you know the weight, as opposed to a
guy who has certain identifying marks on his body and he was
drowned. I mean, really, those are going to be the same circumstances
and the same standards? Or, you know, a גט Get that has
names as opposed to a writ of death when you know there
are guys with the same name, when you don't know there are
guys with the same name. A lot of different cases about what
can you do to determine you're talking about a particular thing or
a particular person, and you know, in the end what really are
the rules, we don't know. It probably depends on a lot of
different factors, and also, as Michael says, why aren't we looking at
other types of supporting evidence? So a lot of things. And we
might, and A, we might, maybe we need to, and it's funny,
the גמרא Gemara sometimes isolates particular aspects in order to clarify that
הלכה, halacha, you know, then but if there's other evidence then we'll
need to discuss that. But it also might be an interesting question
about the difference between evidence versus testimony, right? We know that by
the death case, we don't need formal testimony, for גט Get maybe
we do, and maybe it's a difference of discussion. Again, the גמרא
Gemara is not really clarifying the potentially different standards that are at
play here. Yes, go.
Isn't it possible to read the line וגם לא פרחה vegam la
parcha sarcastically?
Well, that's sort of what Michael was saying, but if it were
sarcastic, then why would it be relevant, then why would we have
to be concerned about it? So it might be sarcastic in the
sense of that it doesn't really matter, once we know there's another
guy with the same name, then we can't ignore him. Right? That
could have been. Except the last possibility of מילי מסר mili masar
makes a really reasonable type of thing.
I understand, like he's saying, the woman has the גט.
Get. Yeah. Well, again, if the גט Get is coming produced by
the person who it's written in the name of, that's a more
obvious case. All these other cases were as if the גט Get
was found on the ground, which is why רבא's Rava example about
the guy with the writ of death producing it, אביי Abaye said
if the guy's producing the writ itself, then it's a much more
obvious situation.
והשתא דאשכחן סהדי Ve-hashta de-ashkachan sahadi means like so they found it
on the floor.
Exactly. Okay. Right.
Right. What did I say? So I've been saying sunflower seeds, oh
I'm so sorry. That changes everything. We gotta go back. That's right
it's sesame seeds I forgot. Sesame seeds are probably a lot more
valuable than sunflower seeds I think anyway. All right. All right. Go
back. Change
everything I told you yesterday was wrong. Sesame seeds. All right. Moving
on. Okay, קטטה בינו לבינה. ktata beino leveina. So that's the first
case in the משנה Mishna where if there's a war in the
world, we don't believe her not because we think she's intentionally lying,
but we think she has made a certain... she might be misinterpreting
the fact, you know, what happened. But if there is peace in
the world but they are fighting, then we're concerned that she might
have... then there's a different concern. Either she intentionally lied or she
is more willing to interpret, you know, vague information that he's dead
because that's what she'd like him to be dead anyway.
So that but that also raises the possibility that she might be
intentionally lying.
What about the large insurance policy?
So okay, קטטה בינו לבינה. ktata beino leveina. You could write that
actually would be a great thing like to write a like, you
know, one of those like murder mysteries based on these פרקים, perakim,
you know, exactly the scenarios in the גמרא Gemara like people do
haikus based on the דף. daf. We could do like a murder
mystery based on it. Okay. So קטטה בינו לבינה. ktata beino leveina.
היכי דמי קטטה? heichi dami ktata? What would be the evidence that
they're fighting, the couple? So you know, so what and היכי דמי
קטטה בינו לבינה? heichi dami ktata beino leveina? אמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel דאומרת לבעלה גרשני. de'omeret le'baalah garsheni.
So she tells her husband, "I've fed up with you, just give
me a divorce already." Okay? So once they... that's what the woman
is saying to her husband, that would satisfy the standard in terms
of then she reports that he died. כולן נמי אמרו הכי. Kulan
nami amru hachi. What are you talking about? All women say this
to their husbands? So רש"י Rashi says when they're angry and fighting,
okay? So everyone, you know, this is a common thing. That's sort
of like, you know, again,
those cases where somebody says, "I'm gonna kill you. I could kill
him." Do you use that as, you know, as supporting evidence that
he was the murderer? So you know, anyway they do this
right now by the way, with like threats like online, Facebook, what
not, and then somebody winds up dead.
No,
not necessarily dead. Okay. All right. Fine. Anyway, so people say that
very often. What does that prove? Maybe they're just angry. אמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel באומרת לבעלה גרשני... be'omeret
le'baalah garsheni... I'm sorry, כולן נמי הכי. kulan nami hachi. אלא באומרת
לבעלה גירשתני. Ela be'omeret le'baalah gerashtani.
No, what she says is she says, "My husband has already divorced
me." She's going around saying, "Yeah, I'm divorced from him." Okay? And
there then the fact that she's making that claim even though we
sort of know it's false is enough to show us that she's
basically checked out of the marriage and she's not interested in being
married to her husband anymore. So the גמרא Gemara says if that's
what she's saying, תיהימנא, teheimna, let's just believe her before we get
to the guy being dead, let's believe her that she is divorced
מדרב המנונא, mi'deRav Hamnuna, based on the statement of רב המנונא. Rav
Hamnuna. דאמר רב המנונא De'amar Rav Hamnuna אשה שאמרה לבעלה גירשתני, isha
she'amra le'baalah gerashtani, a woman who says to her husband that you
have divorced me, נאמנת, ne'emenet, she's believed. חזקה אין אשה מעיזה פניה
בפני בעלה. Chazaka ein isha me'iza paneiha bifnei baalah. A woman would
not be brazen enough to say that straight to her husband's face
if it weren't true. Of course one wonders, what's the husband saying?
If the husband says, "You're lying," right? I mean, so that still
you believe her and so on? But anyway, there is this statement
of רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna that a woman is believed when she
says this. So if that determines that they're fighting, who needs a
whole question about being believed about the guy dying? She should just
already be believed that she's divorced. So the גמרא Gemara says באומרת
גירשתני בפני פלוני ופלוני ושאילנא ואמרינהו לא היו דברים מעולם. be'omeret gerashtani
bifnei ploni u'ploni ve'shailna ve'amreinhu lo hayu devarim me'olam. Finally, a case
that will satisfy Michael that we actually start to do a little
more investigation. She says, "You divorced me in front of ראובן Reuven
and שמעון." Shimon. So she makes... and then we go and ask
ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon and they say, "She's totally making it
up, it never happened."
And she doesn't have a גט. get.
And she doesn't have a גט. get. But the very fact that
she's making that claim shows that she has basically checked out of
the marriage and she's not interested in being married to her husband
anymore. And then if she claims he's dead, then we can't believe
her.
We don't believe her that she's divorced, we're just wondering if he's
really dead.
Right. So of course the question that תוספות Tosafot raises is, if
it's already been established that she's lying when she says that she's
divorced because the witnesses said that she made it up, then why
doesn't that like, you know, completely prove that we can't believe her
when she says the husband is dead? So we'll talk about that
in a minute, but let's take a look at the next line.
What is she saying is she really...
okay. So it says like this: I mean, obviously there could be
other ways of proving that they're, you know, they're always yelling at
each other every single night or something, right? Okay, but anyway, let's
take a look.
מאי טעמא דקטטה? Mai ta'ama de'ktata? What's the reason that when they're
fighting she's not believed? So רב חנינא אמר משום דמשקרא, Rav Chanina
amar mishum de'meshakra, because she'll intentionally lie. Okay, now intentionally lie, what
good is that going to do if the husband is going to
show up? But רש"י Rashi has told us before, yes, but then
she'll have been sleeping with another man, which maybe she wouldn't have
the חוצפה chutzpah to do if בית דין Beis Din didn't פסקן
pasken that the husband was dead. And then the husband shows up,
and because she's been sleeping with another man, she can't go back
to her husband, so she'll manage to get the divorce in the
end anyway. רב שימי בר אשי אמר משום דאמרה בדדמי. Rav Shimi
bar Ashi amar mishum de'amra bedidami. She's not intentionally lying, but since
she's fighting with
Okay, that's what she'd like to see anyway, so you know, that
sort of, which she projects it a little bit. Okay, or it
colors her reading of the circumstances. So מאי בינייהו, mai beinaihu, what
would be a difference between this? Top of כ"ז עמוד ב', Kaf-Zayin
amud beis, איכא בינייהו דאדל הוא קטטה, ika beinaihu de-adal hu ketata,
that he is the reason that they're fighting. It's clear that he's
doing things to annoy her, that she would love it them to
be reconciled and to be married, so presumably, I don't know, she's
not going around saying that they're divorced, so it must be a
different circumstance. Anyway, he's to blame. So if he's to blame, we're
not concerned that she's lying. She wants, it's clear she wants to
stay married. But what we are concerned is is that
because things are still uncomfortable in the marriage and difficult in the
marriage, that might, you know, influence subconsciously her interpretation of the fact,
but she certainly wouldn't be consciously lying in this case. Okay, so
now if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafos, the last of
the wide lines, like five lines from the top, he says, ואם
תאמר, ve-im tomar, four lines,
the תוספות Tosafos on עמוד ב', amud beis, four lines from the
top. ואמאי לא תשקר? ve-amai lo teshaker? Why wouldn't we be concerned
she's lying even in the case when he is to blame? דהא
משקרת, de-ha meshakeret, we already know she's
lying, she's already claimed she's divorced and the witness says it's not
true, then we know she's a confirmed liar. So even if he's
to blame, that should still remain a concern. So the תוספות Tosafos
says,
ויש לומר דזו לא היתה עושה שתשקר לומר מת בעלי. ve-yesh lomar
de-zo lo haysah osah she-teshaker lomar meis ba'ali. It's one thing to
lie to say I'm divorced, but to say my husband is dead,
we know from an earlier פרק perek all of the negative consequences
that are going to be heaped on her if she claimed her
husband was dead and it turns out he's alive. So that far
she won't go, you know, to lie if he's the guy to
blame and she—if he's the reason for the fight and not her.
So it's a little bit convoluted, but basically, you know, it is
interesting based on the גמרא Gemara how the גמרא Gemara set up
the circumstances, it was a case that she was confirmed to have
lied. Okay, but it's funny why that has to be the case
of knowing that they're fighting, there's so many other potential circumstances that
we could establish that the marriage is on the rocks, right? And
the גמרא Gemara gave a very concrete case where she was also
a confirmed liar, okay? Such bracketing that, the תוספות Tosafos tries to
explain why, you know, why that's not as consequential as lying about
death. Okay, but nevertheless, the question is, is it really a concern
of intentional lying or is it a concern just about misinterpretation? And
the difference would be if she's not clearly—if it's not that she
wants him dead, if it's not that, you know, that she wants
out of the marriage, but that he wants out of the marriage.
Okay, and it's maybe a high threshold.
In other words, the marriage can be really terrible but not totally
on the rocks such as קטטה. ketata. קטטה ketata really is like,
that's it.
No, it's a funny thing is though that קטטה ketata is not—does
not sound—קטטה ketata is like, yeah, like fighting, you know? So it's
not clear, right, when the גמרא Gemara gives the example that she
claims she's divorced, like how would that—what would that equal if she
doesn't claim she's divorced but like every night we hear them arguing?
You know, I mean it doesn't help us in terms of normal
circumstances as what is the measure, you know, of this. Now the
גמרא Gemara asks, like it did by the case of מלחמה, milchama,
what about when it's not the woman but an objective עד אחד?
ed echad? And here it's clearer why it would be better. By
the case of מלחמה, milchama, where there's the fog of war, what
difference does an עד אחד ed echad or not? So we had
to say, well, if he's an outside objective witness, maybe he'll be
more precise. But here, since clearly some of this has to do
with her, you know, with her
emotional involvement, the state of the fact that they're at war—that they're
fighting with one another and they're angry at one another and so
on—and that will lead either to intentional lying or to unintentional misinterpretation,
so a third unrelated party, you know, should totally be believed. So
that's the question the גמרא Gemara asks: let's say we know that
the couple has been fighting and the marriage is on the rocks,
and a third party says that the husband died. So the answer
should obviously be okay. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says about
this. איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu, they raised the question: עד אחד בקטטה
מהו? ed echad be-ketata mahu? Do we believe an עד אחד ed
echad when the couple—when the marriage is on the rocks? מאי טעמא
דעד אחד נאמן? mai ta'ama de-ed echad ne'eman? Do we say what's
the reason that one עד אחד ed echad is believed? משום דמילתא
דעבידא לאיגלויי לא משקר, mishum de-milta de-avida le-igluya lo meshaker, somebody won't
lie about something that the facts will come—will, you know, come to
the surface. הכא נמי לא משקר, hacha nami lo meshaker, here too,
if the husband isn't dead, he'll show up, and so guys gotta
be careful before making the claim. או דילמא, o dilma, or do
we say טעמא דעד אחד נאמן משום דהיא דייקא ומינסבא, ta'ama de-ed
echad ne'eman mishum de-hi dayka u-minsava, maybe the reason an עד אחד
ed echad is believed is always because it assumes the backup that
she's going to be double careful before listening to the עד ed
because she doesn't want to have to deal with the consequences if
it turned out he was wrong. Right? Remember all those deep consequences
from the previous פרק. perek. So if every testimony of an עד
אחד ed echad needs her backup, you can't rely on her backup
here,
right? והכא כיון דאית לה קטטה לא דייקא. ve-hacha keivan de-is lah
ketata lo dayka. Now here, that since their marriage is on the
rocks and they're fighting, she's not going to bother to do her
job of the backup and to also investigate. תיקו. Teiku. So the
גמרא Gemara says we don't know. So now it's really complicated, right?
Because now in times when the marriage is in a bad state
or in case of war, not only can you not believe the
woman, but you might not be able to even believe a different
party. Now just imagine that, right? Imagine that let's say you had
the case of 9/11, right, or you had cases of war or
whatever, and not all marriages are in are you know so they
go through bumpy patches, right? And not all marriages are under great
situations. Now all of a sudden you can't believe not only her,
a guy comes back from the battlefield in the Israeli army or
whatever and says I saw, you know, I saw him die. You
can't believe him because we know that the that the marriage was
was on the rocks beforehand, right? So, you know or even if
it's not a מלחמה milchama case, right? Guy just says I was
on a trip with the guy and I saw him die. We
can't believe him? Right? So obviously this raises serious questions about using
these solutions of the עגונה aguna problems that the rabbis came up
with, that now they get severely limited the scope of them, right?
So it's a you know so if we define now maybe you
could say we could define קטטה ketata very narrowly. That's the benefit
of defining קטטה ketata very narrowly is that we won't call it'll
be very hard to claim that any marriage is really in the
קטטה ketata scenario that the גמרא Gemara describes. But we also described
מלחמה milchama pretty broadly, right? And a lot of times people are
reporting back because a building fell down and there was a fire
and there was some tragedy and those would be the you know
a plane went down. Those would be the קטטה ketata types of
those would be the מלחמה milchama types of scenarios. So the ability
to believe עד אחד eid echad in those cases is pretty important.
What do we do?
Yeah, I don't know. We have to I mean that's a much
more I mean we have to give a practical שיעור shiur on
how people on how פוסקים poskim have dealt with these scenarios because
these are the scenarios. Yeah, I mean there's a whole book that
came out about 9/11 and the פסקים psakim that came after 9/11
and then there was a פסקים psakim after the Holocaust and you
know these are regular case areas of הלכה halakha about פסקנינג paskening
about the death of the husband.
Okay, let's see what we mean by by like דייקא ומינסבא. daika
u-minseba.
She investigates before and then she gets married. But first she investigates.
So she would investigate first, right, and then remarry someone else. Exactly.
Right, right.
רבי
יהודה אומר לעולם אינה נאמנת.
Rabbi Yehuda
omer le'olam ein ne'emenet. Rabbi Yehuda says she will not be believed
even in the time of peace and even if the marriage is
good unless she comes in with her garments rent and crying and
her, you know, and all this other evidence. אמרו לו Amru lo
they said to him, אמרו לו לרבי יהודה amru lo le-Rabbi Yehuda
they said to Rabbi Yehuda, דברייך פיקחת תינשא, de-varecha pike'achas tinasei, if
a woman is smart then she can get remarried because she'll know
how she'll know how to act, right? She's a good actress and
she knows that she needs to act. שוטה לא תינשא, Shotah lo
tinasei, and if a woman isn't smart then she's just following, you
know, going following the normal rules of the system but she's not
trying to scheme or to then then she's going to she won't
be allowed to remarry. I mean you're just encouraging people to act.
אלא אחת זו ואחת זו תינשא. Ela achas zu ve-achas zu tinasei.
In either case she can get remarried. We cannot say that it
depends on how the woman is acting. ההוא דאתא לבי דינא. Hahu
de-asa le-vei din. Now a woman came to the בית דין beis
din of Rabbi Yehuda, who would only believe her if she was
clearly in you know sort of in mourning and wailing and so
on. אמרי לה Amri lei and people said to her, here's what
you gotta do honey before you walk into that building. ספדי בעליך,
Sapdi ba'alech, first start eulogizing your husband. Oh, he was so he
was such a great guy. Start that and קרעי מאנייך, karei mana'ich,
rend your garments. Okay, and שיציי מזייך, sipsi maza'ich, undo your hair.
Okay, and and then go ahead and then go in the building
and then then tell Rabbi Yehuda what you know. So the גמרא
Gemara says אפושי שקרא? afu'ei shikra? They taught her how to lie?
So the גמרא Gemara says no, אינהו כרבנן סבירי להו. innu ke-rabbanan
seviri lehu. They held like the rabbis that even without all of
this demonstration she would be believed. So they but they knew that
Rabbi Yehuda wouldn't accept it. So therefore אמרו עביד הכי כי היכי
דלישריי. amru tavid hachi kedei de-yisharei. So they figured they told her
what to do in order to get Rabbi Yehuda to allow it,
even though you know they if they didn't feel that they could
believe her without this they wouldn't have told her that. But they
felt that they could believe the husband was dead but this is
what she would need to do to get Rabbi Yehuda to פסקן
pasken that way. Still though it's it's a type of like לימדו
לשונם דבר שקר, limdu leshonam daber sheker, right? You know it might
be that they got the right result but it was still through
going through a whole little role of a playacting here. All right.
Now בית הלל אומרים. Beis Hillel omrim. So this is the basic
principle. Remember is that a woman is believed to say her husband
died, which is a big חידוש, chiddush, right? We've been dealing with
this for a few פרקים prakim now. But this is where the
גמרא Gemara directly introduces right way before it was a case of
what happens if the husband turned up alive, what's all the consequences.
It sort of assumed the principle that we believe the woman to
say the husband died. But that basic principle... It's coming though. I
know that but that basic principle that you believe the woman was
is introduced in this פרק. perek. It was only assumed in an
earlier פרק, perek, right? So it's so this is the פרק perek
and now it's putting some limits on it. Not a war, not
a fight, but it's basically introducing this tremendously big חידוש chiddush that
you don't need two witnesses and you can trust the woman even
though she's a נוגע בדבר noge'a badavar and even though she's a
woman whose testimony normally isn't accepted. So now we're going to see
that there was a that this started by a concrete case and
there was a debate of בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי
Beis Shammai what lessons could be learned from that concrete case. And
why this next משנה mishna is fascinating. fascinating is A, it's like
a history of הלכה halacha and it's a particularly huge area of
rabbinic innovation. And number two is you see that sometimes בית הלל
Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai and you see sometimes later
תנאים tanna'im inherit פסקים psakim of earlier תנאים tanna'im and then debate
what the scope of those פסקים psakim are. And that's something you
actually, if you're sensitive to it, no, but if you're sensitive to
it, you see that coming up a lot in the משניות. mishnayot.
A debate of interpreting what the earlier פסקים psakim were. So let's
take a look. בית הלל אומרים, Beit Hillel omrim, בית הלל Beit
Hillel says, and here again, ironically, בית הלל Beit Hillel is stringent,
at least initially. לא שמענו אלא בבא מן הקציר ובאותה מדינה כמעשה
שהיה. Lo shama'nu ela be-va min ha-katzir u-ve-otah medinah ke-ma'aseh she-hayah. No,
the only time you can believe a woman is like the case
in which was that served as the precedent for all of this.
So what would that be? It has to be like that case.
It has to be a woman coming back from the harvest, of
the grain harvest, and it has to be she's testifying that the
event occurred in the same country, that the husband died, right, basically,
in the same city. Right. If the husband died, not in some
faraway place, but
in his local area, and similar to the story that occurred.
It has to be like that, like the story that occurred. אמרו
להם בית שמאי, Amru lahem Beit Shammai, בית שמאי Beit Shammai said
back, אחת הבאה מן הקציר, achat ha-ba'ah min ha-katzir, it doesn't matter
whether she's coming from the wheat harvest,
and they were out harvesting wheat and she says that he died,
ואחת הבאה מן הזיתים, ve-achat ha-ba'ah min ha-zeitim, or they came from
harvesting olives, ואחת הבאה מן הבציר, ve-achat ha-ba'ah min ha-batzir, or they
came from harvesting grapes, ואחת הבאה ממדינה למדינה, ve-achat ha-ba'ah mi-medinah le-medinah,
or she came from another distant city and they say that they
were vacationing in Italy and this happened. לא דיברו חכמים בקציר אלא
בהווה. lo dibru chachamim ba-katzir ela ba-hoveh. The reason that they said
that there was a case with the קציר katzir and so on,
that was the case that occurred, but that doesn't mean that those
are the only times you can apply it. ובה חזרו בית הלל
להורות כדברי בית שמאי, ve-koh chazru Beit Hillel le-horot ke-divrei Beit Shammai,
בית הלל Beit Hillel went to rule like בית שמאי. Beit Shammai.
And of course it seems like of course like בית שמאי Beit
Shammai is going to say it's like a reductio ad absurdum. Like
what? It's going to matter whether they were harvesting wheat or harvesting
barley or picking olives? Obviously you have to abstract it. So we're
going to see why בית הלל Beit Hillel feels that yes, you
can abstract it, but not too much. So let's take a look
at the
גמרא. Gemara. תניא, tanya, what's about to say barley. תניא, tanya, what's
about to say barley? Be quiet, everybody, right, תניא, tanya, exactly. אמרו
להם בית שמאי לבית הלל, Amru lahem Beit Shammai le-Beit Hillel, בית
שמאי Beit Shammai said to בית הלל, Beit Hillel, לדבריכם אין לי
אלא קציר חטים. le-divreichem ein li ela katzir chittim. If you guys
are not prepared to be able to abstract and generalize, so it
should only be a wheat harvest. קציר שעורים מניין? katzir se'orim minayin?
How about a barley harvest? אם אין אלא קציר, im ein ela
katzir, I only know harvesting grain. בוצר מוסק גודר אודר מניין? botzer
mosek goder oder minayin? How about doing all different kinds of different
types of work out in the field? Whether it's getting dates or
figs or all these other types of grapes, anything else, how do
you know that would be included? So obviously, a reductio ad absurdum,
you wouldn't say those details would matter. So if those details don't
matter, why do other details matter?
אלא מעשה שהיה בקציר, ela ma'aseh she-hayah ba-katzir, the story was with
the case of a wheat harvest, והוא הדין לכולם, ve-hu ha-din le-kulam,
and it really wouldn't matter. הכי נמי, hachi nami, and you would
presumably agree to that, that it doesn't matter what type of food,
what type of agricultural product they're harvesting. So once you agree to
that, הכי נמי מעשה שהיה באותה מדינה והוא הדין לכולם, hachi nami
ma'aseh she-hayah be-otah medinah ve-hu ha-din le-kulam, you shouldn't demand that it
happen locally, that it happen in the same city, even if it
happen, a woman comes back from a different distant city. ובית הלל,
u-Beit Hillel, בית הלל Beit Hillel would say no. באותה מדינה דשכיחי
אינשי, be-otah medinah de-shchichi inshi, they make a real, maybe it seems
like they're conceding, like I might concede that it doesn't make a
difference what they exactly were doing, but it does matter if she's
coming from a local city or a distant city. If it's a
local city, באותה מדינה דשכיחי אינשי, be-otah medinah de-shchichi inshi, that people
are around, that people would say, what do you mean your husband
died? We were there, right? People know, people know who she is
and they know who the husband is. So if she said he
died in a place where people know him and recognize him and
he didn't die, it's very likely she'll get found out. If she
said we were traveling in China and he died, nobody knows who
they are in China. So she could get away with lying, nobody
would know that it didn't happen. Okay, so here if it's in
the same city that other people are around, מירתתא, mirtata, she's afraid
to lie because people will see that that's not what happened and
they'll recognize the husband.
ממדינה למדינה אחרת, mi-medinah le-medinah acheret, if she reports that it happened
in a different city, דלא שכיחי אינשי, de-la shchichi inshi, that nobody
is around in that distant city that recognizes them, לא מירתתא, la
mirtata, she wouldn't be afraid to lie. ובית שמאי, u-Beit Shammai, what
would בית שמאי Beit Shammai say back? So look, maybe the harvest
shouldn't matter, but there is a big difference between whether it's local
or distant. ובית שמאי ve-Beit Shammai would say back, הכי נמי שכיחי
שיירתא. hachi nami shchichi shayarta. No, there's a lot of travel, there
are caravans, and therefore you won't lie even if you make a
claim about a distant city because the facts will come out regardless.
ובה חזרו בית הלל,
ve-koh chazru
Beit Hillel,
and then in the end בית הלל Beit Hillel agreed. Now, מה
מעשה שהיה? mah ma'aseh she-hayah? What was the original case? דאמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל, de-amar Rav Yehudah amar Shmuel, שילפי קציר חטים היו,
shilfei katzir chittim hayu, it was the end of the period of
harvesting wheat, והלכו עשרה בני אדם לקצור חטים, ve-halchu asarah benei adam
liktzor chittim, and ten people went to harvest the wheat. נשכו נחש
לאחד מהם Nashcho Nachash L'echad Mehem a snake bit one of them
ומת Umeis and he died. ואתא אישתיה והודיעה לבית דין. Ve'atah Ishteia
Vehodiah L'veit Din. Interestingly, although there were ten people there, it's דוקא
davka the wife who came and reported to the בית דין. Beit
Din. ושלחו ומצאו כדבריה Veshalchu Umatzu Kidvareha and they went and they
investigated and they found out she told the truth. So they didn't
just סתם stam believe her. They investigated and they had independent corroboration.
But nevertheless, once they found out that a woman did tell the
truth in this case, it's quite funny how this led to their
פסק. psak. It wasn't like they were forced לפסוק to pasken because
they had no other evidence. It's like, oh look, she told the
truth, let's start believing women. Okay. So I don't really get it.
ובאותה שעה אמרו האישה שאמרה מת בעלי תנשא מת בעלי תתייבם. Uve'otah
Sha'ah Amru Ha'ishah She'amrah Meit Ba'ali Tinasei Meit Ba'ali Tityabeiv. So maybe
what they sort of realized is they said to themselves, what if
we didn't have the supporting evidence? What would we have done then?
You know, and maybe so maybe even though they found a way
לפסוק to pasken it because of supporting evidence, it made them realize
that they had to come up with a certain principle because there
won't always be ten people around. And what's going to happen to
the woman? So that would be pretty powerful that they just realized
what could have happened had they not had it, and that pushed
them to establish this principle. Okay, now what by the way is
the whole issue? Like why could, you know it's a little absurd
because in the משנה Mishnah בית שמאי Beit Shammai בית הלל Beit
Hillel does say it does have to be during the harvest. It's
one thing to say the same city. So take a look at
תוספות. Tosafot. לא דיברו בקציר אלא בהווה. Lo Dibru Bekatzir Ela Bahoveh.
ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, למה
קציר,
Lamah
Katzir, what would, what's special about the time of harvest?
אמר רב מנא דאונסא דשכיח Amar Rav Mannai De'unsa Deshachi'ach שאני החמה
קודחת בראשו של אדם בשעת קציר Shani Hachama Kodachas Berosho Shel Adam
Bish'at Ketzir דאונסא דשכיח שאני. De'unsa Deshachi'ach Shani. Oh, דאונסא דשכיח שאני.
De'unsa Deshachi'ach Shani. החמה קודחת בראשו של אדם בשעת קציר. Hachama Kodachas
Berosho Shel Adam Bish'at Ketzir. You know the sun is burning, right,
sunstroke, beaming down on you, beating down on you I should say.
הדא דכתיב ויגדל הילד ויהי היום ויצא אל אביו אל הקוצרים ויאמר
אל אביו ראשי ראשי. Hadah Dechsiv Vayigdal Hayeled Vayehi Hayom Vayetze El
Aviv El Hakotzrim Vayomer El Aviv Roshi Roshi. Right, remember that case
where the kid comes home and whatever by the אלישע Elisha and
the שונמית? Shunamite? Yeah exactly, and he dies because of the heat
and the sunstroke. Okay, so anyway back to the גמרא. Gemara. But
that's why בית הלל Beit Hillel might have even wanted to have
limited it to that case. Back to the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay. נימא רבי חנינא בן עקיבא ורבנן בפלוגתא דבית שמאי ובית הלל
קמיפלגי. Neimar Rabbi Chanina Ben Akiva Verabbanan Biplogta De'Beit Shammai Ve'Beit Hillel
Kamifligi. We have a similar debate of רבי חנינא בן עקיבא Rabbi
Chanina Ben Akiva and the רבנן Rabbanan about whether you apply things
to the concrete limited cases or you abstract them, and maybe that's
similar to the debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel בית שמאי Beit
Shammai even though בית הלל Beit Hillel reversed himself. דתניא, Detanya, so
it says in a ברייתא. Braisa. לא ישא אדם מי חטאת ואפר
חטאת. Lo Yisa Adam Mei Chatas Ve'eifer Chatas. A person should not
marry, no not carry, should not
carry the ashes of the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, the water for
the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, ויעבירם בירדן, Veya'avireim Bayardein, and pass them,
have them take them over the Jordan River. ובספינה, Uvisfinah, or on
a boat. ולא יעמוד בצד זה ויזרוק בצד זה, Velo Ya'amod Betzad
Zeh Veyizrok Betzad Zeh, not only not on a boat, you cannot
pass them over the Jordan, you can't toss them from one side
to the next. ולא ישיטם על פני המים, Velo Yashitim Al Pnei
Hamayim, or float them on the water like with a raft. ולא
ירכיבם לא על גבי בהמה ולא על גבי חברו, Velo Yarkiveim Lo
Al Gabei Behemah Velo Al Gabei Chaveiro, and you also cannot, let's
say we're not talking about the Jordan, Jordan's too big to do
any of this, but presumably another river as well, you cannot go
ahead and have an animal, put them on the back of an
animal that's going to walk through a river, or have it on
the back of a person who's walking through a river. אלא אם
כן היו רגליו נוגעות בקרקע. Ella Im Kein Hayu Raglav Nogos Bakarka.
The person who's walking through the river, it's okay if his feet
are touching the bottom of the river, but if he's actually on
the animal and he's holding on to it, no. So basically, you
cannot pass it over a river, a body of water, you only,
it can't pass in the air basically or over the water, it
has to be sort of somebody has to be carrying it with
their feet on the ground. Okay, so what we're worried about is
a good question. So let's take a look. אבל מעבירין על הגשר,
Aval Ma'avirin Al Hagesher, but and you can walk over a bridge
because that's like ground. Okay, his feet are touching ground, they're touching
the bridge, but touching the deck of a boat wouldn't count, but
a bridge is connected to the ground so that counts. Okay. מעבירין
על הגשר אחד ירדן ואחד שאר נהרות, Ma'avirin Al Hagesher Echad Yarden
Ve'echad Shear Neharos, whether the Jordan or whether any other river. רבי
חנינא בן עקיבא אומר לא אמרו אלא ירדן, Rabbi Chanina Ben Akiva
Omer Lo Amru Ella Yardein, no, the only time it's prohibited is
the Jordan River ובספינה Uvisfinah and in a boat, not these other
ways of getting something over the river. וכמעשה שהיה, Ukema'aseh Shehayah, like
the original case. Okay, and we'll find out about an original case
where they were passing, taking some ashes of a פרה אדומה Parah
Adumah over the Jordan and it became טמא, tamei, and that led
to them to make a more general prohibition. So you see there's
a question about applying things to like limiting them to their original
case or not. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. למימרא דרבנן
דאמרי כבית שמאי, Leimeira Rabanan De'amri KeBeit Shammai, the רבנן Rabanan who
broaden it say like בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, ורבי חנינא בן עקיבא
דאמר כבית הלל, VeRabbi Chanina Ben Akiva De'amar KeBeit Hillel, and רבי
חנינא בן עקיבא Rabbi Chanina Ben Akiva who narrows it says like
בית הלל, Beit Hillel, even though בית הלל Beit Hillel reversed himself.
So no, אמרי לך רבנן, Amrei Lach Rabanan, the רבנן Rabanan could
say to you, אנן דאמרינן כבית הלל, Anan De'amrinan KeBeit Hillel, we
would say even in theory we could be narrow like בית הלל
Beit Hillel in his case. But עד כאן לא קאמר בית הלל
התם, Ad Kan Lo Ka'amar Beit Hillel Hatam, why was בית הלל
Beit Hillel narrow in the case of reporting the death of a
husband? אלא משום דמירתתא Ella Mishum Demirtata דמירתתא, Demirtata, that the reason
you believe her is she's afraid to lie,
במקום קרוב דמירתתא. Bemakom Karov Demirtata. Locally or it happened far away,
she'll be more prepared to lie if it happened far away, she
won't be afraid. So that makes sense not to broaden it too
much. Okay, but הכא מאי לירדן מאי שאר נהרות hacha mai l'yarden
mai she'ar naharos here if we're gonna make a problem about transferring
something over over the Jordan, what difference does it make if it's
the Jordan or another river? I mean we'll see what problem it
is in general, but there's no logic to distinguish the Jordan and
other rivers. There's a logic to distinguish local versus a distant country.
Okay, so that's number one. You can't compare it that way. And
רבי חנינא בן עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Chanina ben Akiva omer, Rabbi Chanina
ben Akiva would say to you, אנא דאמרי אפילו כבית שמאי, ana
d'amri afilu keBeis Shammai, I could go even going בית שמאי Beis
Shammai who generalizes. עד כאן לא קאמר בית שמאי התם, ad kan
lo ka'amar Beis Shammai hasam,
the reason בית שמאי Beis Shammai is prepared to generalize in the
case of the woman, אלא משום דדייקא ומינסבא, ela mishum d'dayka u'minsava,
is because a woman will investigate and before she gets married and
she'll be afraid of the consequences, so there's a logic to apply
that to all cases. מה לי מקום קרוב ומה לי מקום רחוק,
ma li makom karov u'ma li makom rachok, they're not concerned whether
it's local or far away. A woman will always be afraid that
she'll be found out and of the consequences and it'll always so
therefore there's a reason to generalize there and to abstract. But here,
הכא משום מעשה שהיה בירדן ובספינה דהוי מעשה גזרו רבנן בשאר נהרות
דלא הוי מעשה לא גזרו רבנן. hacha mishum ma'aseh shehayah b'Yarden u'vesfinah
d'hava ma'aseh gazru rabbanan b'she'ar naharos d'lo hava ma'aseh lo gazru rabbanan.
Here what it's basically saying is here there's not so much of
a logic why we forbid this thing anyway. Okay, there's why can't
you transfer the ashes of the פרה אדומה parah adumah over body
of water? So since there's no logic to it, we might as
well apply it to only the very narrow concrete circumstances that it
originally occurred. We're not going to there there's a reason, we want
the woman to remarry, there's a logic to believe her, so we're
going to want to abstract it and apply it broad. Here there's
no real reason to say it should be a problem, there was
just an event that we felt we had to react to. So
since it's only arbitrary and we're reacting to an event, we're going
to limit it to the specifics of that event. Now what was
that event? Let's go to it. מה מעשה שהיה? ma ma'aseh shehayah?
דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב מעשה באדם אחד שהיה מעביר מי חטאת
ואפר חטאת בירדן ובספינה, d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav ma'aseh b'adam echad
shehayah ma'avir mei chatas v'efer chatas b'Yarden u'vesfinah, he was transferring the
ashes of the פרה אדומה parah adumah over the Jordan in a
boat, ונמצא כזית מן המת תחוב בקרקעיתה של ספינה, v'nimtza kezayis min
hames tachuv b'karkisa shel sefinah, and they found a little piece of
a human corpse in you know in some section in the boat
and it made everything in the boat טמא tamei and it made
the ashes טמא, tamei, so באותה שעה אמרו, b'osah sha'ah amru, that's
when they said, לא ישא אדם מי חטאת ואפר חטאת ויעבירם בירדן
ובספינה, lo yisa adam mei chatas v'efer chatas v'ya'avirem b'Yarden u'vesfinah, don't
do this ever again. But there's no real logic, I mean accidents
will always happen, right? So he says since there's no real logic
of course there I'll say let's leave this גזרה gezeirah and this
reaction to as limited of an application as possible. But here, of
course we want to make it broader, we want to allow the
woman to remarry, we have a reason why we want to say
this, and there's a logic to be able to apply it in
all cases and therefore we will. And in the end בית הלל
Beis Hillel winds up ruling like בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, which is
obviously critical.
But בית שמאי Beis Shammai is the one that says there's שיירות,
shayaros, so if it was if it really was like one of
these like places without שיירות shayaros they wouldn't say it, they wouldn't
believe it?
What?